Guide to the Nicholas Georgescu-Roegen Papers, 1930-1994 RL.00442
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Nicholas Georgescu-Roegen papers
1930-1994
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Georgescu-Roegen, Nicholas
Econometric Society
RL.00442
46.5 Linear Feet 31 boxes
46.5 lin. ft. (31 boxes)
The bulk of the collection consists of Georgescu's writings and lectures, correspondence, research and subject files, audiovisual recordings, and engagement files. Most materials date from the 1960s-1980s and relate to Georgescu's professional life as a professor at Vanderbilt University. Notable correspondents include Joseph Schumpter, Friedrich von Hayek, Paul Samuelson, and other preeminent economists. Georgescu's work as editor for Econometrica and his extensive writings on entropy and utility are also represented in the collection. A small portion of materials date from his administrative work as a Romanian official. Typed transcripts and other documents reveal details concerning political conditions in Romania during the period of the provisional government and the Armistice trials following World War II. During this period Georgescu-Roegen served the new government in various capacities before he fled the country with his wife in 1948.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library received the Nicholas Georgescu-Roegen papers as a gift in 1995 and 2000.
Biographical Note
Nicholas Georgescu-Roegen (1906-1994) was born in Constantsa, Romania. He studied mathematics at the University of Bucharest and graduated in 1926. He earned his doctorate in statistics from the Sorbonne in 1930 and become a professor of statistics at the University of Bucharest. He spent 1934 through 1936 at Harvard University, and worked with Joseph Schumpeter and Wassily Leontif. Their research influenced Georgescu's work in mathematical economics. Although Schumpeter invited Georgescu to stay at Harvard, he returned to Romania in 1934 as both a professor and government official (working several positions, including as the head of the Romanian Armistice Commission) until the Communist revolution in 1948 forced him and his wife, Otilia, to flee the country. The couple made their way back to the United States in 1949, where Georgescu joined the economics faculty at Vanderbilt University.
Georgescu had widespread economic interests, but is especially noted as a pioneer of bioeconomics, also referred to as evolutionary or ecological economics. His research and writings apply the entropy law of thermodynamics to economical activity in markets and society.
Collection Overview
The bulk of the collection consists of Georgescu's writings and lectures, correspondence, research and subject files, audiovisual recordings, and engagement files. Most materials date from the 1960s-1980s and relate to Georgescu's professional life as a professor at Vanderbilt University. Notable correspondents include Joseph Schumpter, Friedrich von Hayek, Paul Samuelson, and other preeminent economists. Georgescu's work as editor for Econometrica and his extensive writings on entropy and utility are also represented in the collection. A small portion of materials date from his administrative work as a Romanian official. Typed transcripts and other documents reveal details concerning political conditions in Romania during the period of the provisional government and the Armistice trials following World War II. During this period Georgescu-Roegen served the new government in various capacities before he fled the country with his wife in 1948.
Materials have been arranged into series, which include: Correspondence, Writings, Research/Subject Files, Engagements, Teaching, Romania, Biographical Files, Audiovisual Materials, and Writings by Others.
Consumer behavior; Economics, Mathematical; Entropy; Economic development -- Environmental aspects; Time and economic reactions; Value; Audiotapes; Romania -- History -- 1944-1989; Romania -- Politics and government; Economists -- Correspondence; World War, 1939-1945 -- Romania; Economics -- Study and teaching; Agriculture -- Economic aspects; Romania -- Politics and government; Economists -- United States -- History; Economic history -- United States; Georgescu-Roegen, Nicholas; Samuelson, Paul A. (Paul Anthony), 1915-2009; Schumpeter, Joseph Alois, 1883-1950; Arrow, Kenneth J. (Kenneth Joseph), 1921-2017; Econometric Society; Econometric Society; Econometric Society
- Writings, 1930-1994 and undated; 1
  Scope and Contents
  The largest series in the collection, the Writings Series contains the bulk of Georgescu's articles, lectures, and related materials, as well as some materials related to his published books. The series has been sorted into subseries: General Works, which includes scholarly articles, conference papers, chapter contributions, and other essays; Books, which includes extensive materials from some of Georgescu's books, but incomplete documentation from other works; Writings about Romania, which contains drafts and notes from Georgescu's unpublished research on Romanian history and Romanian peasantry; and Speeches.
  - General, 1
    Arrangement
    Articles, essays, and other writings are arranged alphabetically by title. Book reviews and opinion columns are foldered together at the end of the subseries.
    - About Economic Growth: A Variation on a Theme by David Hilbert. Closing Remarks by NGR, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Amintiri Despre Gazeta Matematica, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Analytics versus Dialetics in Economics, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Analytical Representation of Economic Decisions under Multiple Criteria, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Are the Least Action Principle and Other Economic Laws Laws of Nature?, 1987 and undated (Box 1)
    - Are their [sic] minds that may think above their time? An Exordium, undated (Box 1)
    - Are There Minds that Think above their Time? The Case of Hermann Heinrich Gossen, 1984 (Box 1)
    - Asupra Problemei 5527, 1947 (Box 1)
    - A Bioeconomic Viewpoint, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Bioeconomics, undated (Box 1)
    - Bioeconomics: A New Look at the Nature of Economic Activity, 1979 and undated (Box 1)
    - Bioeconomic Aspects of Entropy, 1975 (Box 1)
    - Bioeconomics or Economics?, 1975 and undated (Box 1)
    - Bioeconomics and Ethics, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Biographical Dictionary of Dissenting Economists, 1990 and undated (Box 1)
    - Calcul des Probabilites, 1930 (Box 1)
    - Carnot Cycle, 1982 and undated (Box 1)
    - Chamberlin's New Economics and the Unit of Production, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Change, Order, and Chance (Chapter E), undated (Box 1)
    - Change, Order, and Disorder, undated (Box 1)
    - Choice and Revealed Preference, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Choice, Expectations, and Measurability, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Comments on the Papers by Daly and Stiglitz, 1979 (Box 1)
    - Commentaire: Sadi Carnot et L'essor de la Thermodynamique, 1974 (Box 1)
    - The Crisis of Natural Resources, 1981 (Box 1)
    - The Crisis of Resources: Its Nature and Its Unfolding, 1980-1987 (Box 1)
    - A Critique of Statistical Principles in Relation to Social Phenomena, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Cunoastere si Dialectica; Contributii la Economia si Filozofia Sciintifica, 1974 (Box 1)
    - De la Science Economique a la Bioeconomie, 1978 (Box 1)
    - La Degradation Entropique et la Destinee Prometheenne de la Technologie Humaine, 1982 (Box 1)
    - A Different Economic Perspective, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Does Life Matter?, undated (Box 1)
    - Dynamic Models and Economic Growth, 1973-1977 (Box 1)
    - Economia dell'ambiente (introduction), 1988 (Box 1)
    - Economia e degradazione della Materia, 1985 (Box 1)
    - L'economia Politica come Estensione della Biologia, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Economia Productiei, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Economic Activity Analysis, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Economic Growth and Its Representation by Models, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Economic Theory and Agrarian Economics, 1960-1973 (Box 1)
    - Economics and Educational Development, 1976 (Box 1)
    - Economics and Entropy, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Economics and Mankind's Ecological Problem, 1976 (Box 1)
    - The Economics of Production, 1970 (Box 1)
    - The Elasticity of Substitution versus the Marshallian Elasticity, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Elementary Analysis of the Concept of Production Function (Chapter B), undated (Box 1)
    - An Emigrant from a Developing Country: Autobiographical Notes I, 1988 (Box 1)
    - An Emigrant from a Developing Country: Autobiographical Notes I, 1988 and undated (Box 2)
    - Energetic Dogma, Energetic Economics, and Viable Technologies, 1982 (Box 2)
    - The Energetic Dogma, Energy Analysis, and Technology Assessment, 1978 (Box 2)
    - The Energetic Theory of Economic Value: A Topical Fallacy, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Energy Analysis and Economic Valuation, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Energy Analysis and Technology Assessment, 1982 (Box 2)
    - Energy and Economic Myths, 1975, 1982 (Box 2)
    - Energy, Economics, and the Environment: Reply by NGR, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Energy and Matter in Mankind's Technological Circuit, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
    - Energy, Matter, and Economic Valuation, 1980 and undated (Box 2)
    - Energy, Matter, and Economics: A Holistic View, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - Energy, Matter, and Technological Assessment, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Energy, Technology, and Society, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Entropy, undated (Box 2)
    - The Entropy Law and the Economic Problem, 1970 (Box 2)
    - The Entropy Law and the Economic Process, 1975 (Box 2)
    - Entropy Law and the Economic Process: A Global Viewpoint, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Entropy Law and Economic Process in Retrospect, 1984-1986 (Box 2)
    - An Epistemological Analysis of Statistics: The Science of Collective Description and of Rational Guessing, 1983 (Box 2)
    - An Epistemological Analysis of Statistics as the Science of Rational Guessing, 1967 (Box 2)
    - O Estrangulamento - Inflacao Estrutural e o Cresimento Economico, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Evolution: A Fluxation of Surprises, Not a Flow of Believeds, undated (Box 2)
    - Feasible Recipes versus Viable Technologies, 1984-1988 (Box 2)
    - Fixed Coefficients of Production and the Marginal Productivity Theory, undated (Box 2)
    - A Fundamental Property of Systems Characterized by Nonnegative Matrices… Discussion, 1953 (Box 2)
    - Further Contributions to the Sampling Problem, 1932 (Box 2)
    - Further Thoughts on Corrado Gini's Delusioni dell'econometria, 1966 (Box 2)
    - General Reflections on the Theme of Innovations, 1980 (Box 2)
    - A Historical Perspective of Possible Bridges Between the Economic and Natural Domains, 1989 and undated (Box 2)
    - The Human Species at a Crossroad, 1977 (Box 3)
    - O Impasse de Inflacao Estrutural e o Desenvolvimento Equilabrado, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Imperfection de L'information, Incertitude et Concurrence (preface), 1981 (Box 3)
    - Independence Theorems for a Class of Sampling Subjects, 1964 (Box 3)
    - Inequality, Limits, and Growth from a Bioeconomic Viewpoint, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Influence de L'age Maternel, du rang de Naissance, et de L'ordre des Naissances sur la Mortinata Lite, 1937 (Box 3)
    - An Input-Output Analysis of Marx's Reproduction Scheme, undated (Box 3)
    - The Institutional Aspects of Peasant Economies: A Historical and Analytical Review, 1965-1969 (Box 3)
    - International Energy Studies foreword, undated (Box 3)
    - The Interplay between Institutional and Material Factors: The Problem and its Status, 1988 (Box 3)
    - The Interplay of Economic and Institutional Factors, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Is Entropy Bootlegging Possible?, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Is the Perpetual Motion of the Third Kind Possible?, 1976-1977 and undated (Box 3)
    - La Ley de la Entropia y el Problema Economico, 1978 (Box 3)
    - L'Environment Economique, Social et Politique de l'entreprise d'ici la fin du Siecle, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Leontiff's System in the Light of Recent Results, 1950 (Box 3)
    - Logical and Empirical Foundations of Economic Development, undated (Box 3)
    - Looking Back, 1991 (Box 3)
    - Man and Production, 1984 (Box 3)
    - Mankind at a Bioeconomic Crossroad, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
    - Marginal Utility of Money and Elasticities of Demand, 1936 (Box 3)
    - Marx's Scheme of Reproduction and Value Theory, undated (Box 3)
    - Mathematical Proofs of the Breakdown of Capitalism, 1960 (Box 3)
    - Matter: A Resource Ignored by Thermodynamics-Renewable Resource Economics, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Matter Matters, Too, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Mea Culpa, undated (Box 3)
    - The Measure of Information: A Critique, 1975 (Box 3)
    - Measure, Quality, and Optimum Scale, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Mechanistic Dogma and Economics, 1974-1978 (Box 3)
    - Methods in Economic Science, 1979-1981 (Box 3)
    - Metados em Ciencia Economica, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Modificari Structurale in Venitul National al Romaniei, 1947 (Box 3)
    - A Multidimensional Generalization of the Bienayme-Chebyshev Theorem, 1975 (Box 3)
    - My Life Philosophy, 1990-1991 (Box 4)
    - Myths about Energy and Matter, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Natural Resources: The Laws and Their Scarcity, 1982 (Box 4)
    - The Nature of Expectation and Uncertainty, 1955 and undated (Box 4)
    - The New Economics, 1975 (Box 4)
    - Note on the Economic Equilibrium for Nonlinear Models, 1954 (Box 4)
    - Note on Holley's Dynamic Model in Econometrica, 1953 (Box 4)
    - Note on the Main Proposition of Distribution Theory, undated (Box 4)
    - Note on a Proposition of Pareto, undated (Box 4)
    - On a Class of Probability Distribution, undated (Box 4)
    - On Neo-Populism and Marxism: A Comment on Utsa Patnaik, 1981 (Box 4)
    - On the Case of Catalytic Labor, 1970 (Box 4)
    - On the Extrema of Some Statistical Coefficients, 1959 (Box 4)
    - On the Relation of Binary and Multiple Choices: Some Comments and Further Results, 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    - On the Total Extension of a Partial Order, undated (Box 4)
    - Overpopulation and Agrarian Policy, undated (Box 4)
    - Perpetual Motion of the Third Kind and the Economics of Natural Resources, undated (Box 4)
    - Plant, Firm, Industry, undated (Box 4)
    - The Present Status of Utility Theory, undated (Box 4)
    - Privatization: A Word in Search of a Denotation, 1992 (Box 4)
    - Le Probleme de la Recherche des Composantes Cycliques d'un Phenomene, 1930 (Box 4)
    - Process Analysis and the Neoclassical Theory of Production, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Process in Farming versus Process in Manufacturing: A Problem of Balanced Development, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Process, Value, and Development, 1963 (Box 4)
    - Production Function, undated (Box 4)
    - Production Process and Dynamic Economics, undated (Box 4)
    - The Promethean Condition of Viable Technologies, 1982-1983 (Box 5)
    - The Pure Theory of Consumer's Behavior, 1936 (Box 5)
    - Quo Vadis Homo Sapiens Sapiens?, 1989 (Box 5)
    - Recollections, Part 2, 1990-1992 and undated (Box 5)
    - Reply to Daly and Umana's Economics, Ecology, and Energy postscript, 1981 (Box 5)
    - Revisiting Marshall's Constancy of Marginal Utility of Money, 1968 (Box 5)
    - The Role of Matter in the Substitution of Energies, 1979 (Box 5)
    - Romanian Academy, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
    - Sabin Manuila, 1967 (Box 5)
    - Satiety, undated (Box 5)
    - The Scarcity of Materials, undated (Box 5)
    - Scatter Analysis, 1947 (Box 5)
    - Simple Process and Its Coordinates (Chapter A), undated (Box 5)
    - Some Thoughts on Growth Models: A Reply, 1963 (Box 5)
    - Stabilizing the Currency by a Communist Government: The Romania Case, undated (Box 5)
    - Lo Stato Stazionario e la Salvezza Ecologica, 1984 (Box 5)
    - The Steady State and the Ecological Problem, undated (Box 5)
    - The Steady State and Ecological Salvation: A Thermodynamic Analysis, 1977 (Box 5)
    - Structural Inflation-Lock and Balanced Growth, 1970 (Box 5)
    - Structure and Involuntary Unemployment, 1979 (Box 5)
    - Sur la Meilleure Valeur a Posteriori D'une Variable Aleatoire, 1935 (Box 6)
    - Symposium on Technology and Public Policy discussion text, 1975 (Box 6)
    - The Tableau Economique, undated (Box 6)
    - Technology Assessment: The Case of the Direct Use of Solar Energy, 1978 (Box 6)
    - La Teoria Energetica del Valor Economico: Un Sofisma Economico Particular, 1983 (Box 6)
    - Theorie Economique et Economie Politique Agraire, 1967 (Box 6)
    - Theory and Economic Reality, undated (Box 6)
    - The Theory of Choice and the Constancy of Economic Laws, 1950 (Box 6)
    - Thermodynamics and We, the Humans, 1991 (Box 6)
    - Thermodynamics, Economics, and Information, 1985-1989 (Box 6)
    - Threhold in Choice and the Theory of Demand, 1958 (Box 6)
    - Time and Change (Chapter D), undated (Box 6)
    - Time and Change in Economics, 1985 and undated (Box 6)
    - Time and Evolution, undated (Box 6)
    - Time and Scarcity in Gossen's Economic System, 1984 (Box 6)
    - Time and Value in Economics and in Gossen's System, 1985 (Box 6)
    - Time in Economics, 1980 and undated (Box 6)
    - Time in Economics, 1994 (Box 6)
    - Topics in Analytical Economics, undated (Box 6)
    - Toward Partial Redirection of Econometrics, 1952 (Box 6)
    - Utility, undated (Box 6)
    - Utility, 1969-1972 (Box 6)
    - Utility, 1964-1968 (Box 6)
    - Utility, undated (Box 7)
    - Utility, 1968 (Box 7)
    - Utility, 1982-1993 (Box 7)
    - Utility, undated (Box 7)
    - Utility, Expectations, Measurability, Prediction, 1952-1953 (Box 7)
    - Utility, Value, and Consumer Behavior, undated (Box 7)
    - Value Theory and the Consumer's Behavior, 1966 (Box 7)
    - A Variation about Growth on a Theme by David Hilbert, 1988 (Box 7)
    - Vectors and Matrices: Basic Theorems (Appendix A), undated (Box 7)
    - Vilfredo Pareto and his Theory of Ophelimity, 1973 (Box 7)
    - Das Wechspelspiel von Institutionellen und Materiellen Faktoren: das Problem und sein Status, undated (Box 7)
    - What Thermodynamics and Biology can Teach Economists, 1977 (Box 7)
    - Why We Cannot Get By without Dialectics, 1977 (Box 7)
    - Book reviews by NGR, 1951-1973 (Box 7)
    - Opinion columns by NGR, 1970-1979 (Box 7)
  - Writings about Romania, 2
    Georgescu's longstanding interest in Romania and his intention to publish scholarly work about the region is documented in this subseries. Materials have been divided based on what appears to be two separate projects: one monograph on the Basarabian region, and one on the history of Romanian peasantry. There is substantial overlap between these books, and it appears that Georgescu's projects evolved over time. Unfortunately the drafts are largely undated. Also represented here is Georgescu's work as an editor and contributor to the Mid-European Studies Center, which intended to publish resources on Romania in the 1950s.
    - Basarabia work, 1950s-1960s
      - Basarabia draft and cover letter to the Mid-European Studies Center, 1955 (Box 8)
      - Basarabia introduction, Chapter 1 drafts, undated (Box 8)
      - Basarabia draft/excerpt, untitled, undated (Box 8)
      - Basarabia maps, undated (Box 8)
      - Chapter 1 draft: Basarabia Survey, undated (Box 8)
      - Chapter 3 draft: Eastern Question and the Romanian Principalities, undated (Box 8)
      - Chapter 1 drafts: Russia, Romania, and Basarabia, undated (Box 8)
      - Basarabia Under Romanian Rules chapter draft, with notes, undated (Box 8)
      - Basarabia and its Romanian Past draft, undated (Box 8)
      - Draft excerpts, Version B, undated (Box 8)
      - Chapters 1 and 2 drafts, Version A, undated (Box 8)
      - Draft, "incomplete version", undated (Box 8)
      - Chapters 1 and 2 drafts, undated (Box 8)
      - Chapters 3 and 4 drafts, undated (Box 8)
      - Chapter 5 draft, undated (Box 8)
      - Chapters 6 and 7, undated (Box 8)
      - Basarabia miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 8)
      - Romania, Russia, and Basarabia drafts, Version C, undated (Box 8)
    - Romanian Peasantry work, 1950s-1960s
      - Romanian Peasantry: The National Peasants drafts, undated (Box 9)
      - Chapter draft: By Ourselves, undated (Box 9)
      - Introduction draft, 1954 (Box 9)
      - Chapter 2 drafts, untitled, undated (Box 9)
      - Chapter 1 draft: The Land, undated (Box 9)
      - Chapter 2 draft: The Past, undated (Box 9)
      - Population chapter drafts, undated (Box 9)
      - Chapter drafts: National Peasants, The Past, undated (Box 9)
      - Agriculture chapter drafts, undated (Box 9)
      - Agriculture chapter drafts, undated (Box 10)
      - National Income/National Wealth chapter, 1950 (Box 10)
      - Economic and General comments, undated (Box 10)
      - The Land and the People, undated (Box 10)
      - Draft, Chapters 1-6, undated (Box 10)
      - Draft: Introduction, Chapters 1-3, undated (Box 10)
      - Draft with unknown excerpts, undated (Box 10)
      - Contents, outlines, notes, undated (Box 10)
      - Draft pages: Introduction, Agriculture, Population, undated (Box 10)
    - Mid-European Studies Center Romanian Handbook Project, 1949-1957
      - Economic and Social Structure of the Romanian People draft, undated (Box 11)
      - Economic and Social Structure of the Romanian People draft, undated (Box 11)
      - Chapter excerpts sent to NGR for comments, 1955 (Box 10)
      - The Armistice Convention and its Application, undated (Box 10)
      - A History of Some History of Romania, undated (Box 10)
      - Romanian Handbook project, 1949-1957 (Box 10)
  - Books, 3
    This subseries includes incomplete drafts, correspondence, and reviews of several of Georgescu's books, including Agrarian Economics, Entropy Law and Economic Process, and Bioeconomics. The bulk of the subseries documents Georgescu's work with a translation of The Development of the Laws of Human Intercourse and the Consequent Rules of Human Action (1954) by Hermann Heinrich Gossen (1810-1958), which was accomplished by Rudolf Blitz. Georgescu believed Gossen to have been an unjustly unrecognized inventor of the general theory of marginal utility. His 130-page introduction to the translation consumed over a decade of work, all of which is present.
    - Agrarian Economics correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 11)
    - Agrarian Economics drafts, undated (Box 11)
    - Agrarian Economics research, undated (Box 11)
    - Analytical Economics: Issues and Problems publisher correspondence, 1963-1967 (Box 11)
    - Analytical Economics: Issues and Problems correspondence re: Italian translation, 1966-1973 (Box 11)
    - Analytical Economics: Issues and Problems reviews, 1967-1984 (Box 11)
    - Bioeconomics publisher correspondence, drafts of introduction/preface, 1984 (Box 12)
    - Entropy Law and Economic Process publisher correspondence, 1970-1976, 1990-1993 (Box 12)
    - Entropy Law and Economic Process reviews, 1971-1972 (Box 12)
    - Entropy: A New Worldview foreword drafts, 1979-1980 (Box 12)
    - Entropy: A New Worldview foreword correspondence and reviews, 1980 (Box 12)
    - Entropy: A New Worldview: NGR's response to Irving Kristol in Wall Street Journal, 1980-1981 (Box 12)
    - Gossen Project: Correspondence with Rudolph Blitz and publisher Augustus Kelly, 1966-1978 (Box 12)
    - Gossen Project: Correspondence with F. A. Hayek, 1969-1982 (Box 12)
    - Gossen Project: Mathematical notes, undated (Box 12)
    - Gossen Project: Working references, undated (Box 12)
    - Gossen Project: Notes on Blum on Gossen, undated (Box 12)
    - Articles for research on Gossen project, undated (Box 12)
    - Hermann Heinrich Gossen drafts and fragments, 1973 and undated (Box 12)
    - Hermann Heinrich Gossen drafts and fragments, undated (Box 13)
    - Gossen's The Laws of Human Relation and the Rules of Human Action Derived Therefrom translation drafts, undated (Box 13)
    - Corrections to Gossen translation, undated (Box 13)